Finding Aid for Bureau of School Services (University of Michigan) Records 1871-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bureau of School Services (University of Michigan) records 1871-1992
University of Michigan. Bureau of School Services.
166 linear feet
University of Michigan unit established in 1871 to accredit secondary schools. Consists primarily of accreditation inspection reports, 1871-1992, representing over 1,000 public and private high schools in Michigan. Reports include information on demographics, facilities, finances, curriculum, staffing, and reviewers comments. Some early reports were completed by John Dewey. Files are arranged by school alphabetically by city. The state assumed accreditation responsibility in 1992.
8727 Bimu C5 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was received in two accessions: 1953 and 1996 (donor no. 3008 ).
The records are open for research.
In 1871 the University of Michigan became the first university in the United States to drop the admissions requirement of entrance examinations and offer instead a program of voluntary accreditation to public, private, and parochial secondary schools. Michigan high schools that wanted to enter into this arrangement were visited by a university faculty committee that appraised the schools for their work in science, philosophy, and the arts. A school that passed the minimum criteria in all three areas would be accredited. By 1876 accreditation specifications had changed to accommodate schools that were strong in only one or two of the subject areas. Students from these schools would be granted entrance to select university programs depending on the accreditation status of the secondary school from which they graduated. During the early years of the program, requests for accreditation came from outside of the state, including schools in California, Massachusetts, Illinois, Indiana, and Ohio. In 1884 admission to the University of Michigan by diploma was extended to high schools outside of Michigan. By May of 1900, a single system of entrance requirements went into effect.
Five Michigan high schools were accredited the first year, these being Adrian High School, Ann Arbor High School, Central High School of Detroit, Central High School of Flint, and Jackson High School. In 1900 there were 127 accredited schools. By 1951 this number had reached 635.
In 1899, at the recommendation of the faculty of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, the Board of Regents agreed that an individual was needed to oversee the accreditation program on a full-time basis. Thus, Alan S. Whitney, who went on to become chair of the Department of Education and the first dean of the School of Education, was appointed the first full-time inspector of high schools. He was followed in 1914 by Dr. James B. Edmonson, who later became the second dean of the School of Education. In 1929 Dr. George E. Carrothers became director of what had come to be known as the Division of University Inspection of High Schools. In 1932 the unit was reorganized and renamed as the Bureau of Cooperation with Educational Institutions.
In 1948 the Board of Regents authorized the establishment of the Bureau of School Services, effectively combining the activities of the Bureau of Educational Reference and Research, the Bureau of Cooperation with Educational Institutions, and other support units. The Bureau's administrative hierarchy consisted of a director, who reported directly to the Board of Regents, and a coordinating or executive committee consisting of deans, professors, and administrators appointed by the Board of Regents. Provost James P. Adams remarked that "The establishment of the Bureau of School Services will make possible the extension and development of the University's services to schools and the communities of the State." (Letter to Schools, vol. 1, no. 1, June 1948). The Bureau's function, as explained by the provost, was to coordinate within the university the activities previously carried out by a number of separate agencies. It was to extend the services already provided and develop new services to the schools as needed. Additionally, it would act as a central office of communication with the schools regarding the services of the university. Over the years, the services provided to both public and private high schools have included consulting services in a variety of areas such as testing and evaluation, libraries, area studies, journalism, and curriculum. The Bureau also sponsored and directed a number of conferences, including the annual Citizenship Conference; the Conference for School Board Members, School Officials, and Laymen; Cheerleaders' Clinics; Forensic Day; Secondary School Conference of the Schoolmasters Club; and a number of area conferences and smaller meetings between school administrators and university representatives.
In 1970 oversight of the Bureau of School Services was moved to the School of Education. The director reported to the assistant dean of Services and Institutional Relations. The executive committee was replaced by a University Advisory Committee, which was chaired by the dean of the School of Education and composed of the Administrative Dean of the Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs and the deans of the College of Engineering, the School of Music, and the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts.
The accreditation program provided minimum standards for secondary schools to seek to attain and surpass. Accreditation visits took place once every five to seven years by a university appointed accreditation consultant, meaning that each year approximately one-fifth of the accredited high schools were visited in any given year. During the visit teachers and programs were evaluated. These evaluations were combined with a report that was submitted by the school to determine accreditation status. In addition to its accreditation function, the Bureau also served as a liaison between the Michigan State Department of Education and the various school districts.
In 1983 a review committee evaluating the School of Education recommended closure of the Bureau. At this point the Bureau continued, but was pushed to become a self-supporting entity. In 1984, following a reorganization of the School of Education, the Bureau became part of the Bureau of School Improvement and Standards, which was subsequently reorganized as the Bureau of Accreditation and School Improvement Studies. The Bureau of School Services finally closed in 1992 when the Michigan State Department of Education took over accreditation activity.
The North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools was a somewhat separate accreditation agency that maintained close ties with the university's accreditation program. The Association began in 1895 and maintained its main office at the University of Michigan. Some of its files were transferred with those of the Bureau of School Services and are inter-filed within the Bureau's accreditation inspection reports. The North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools still maintains a regional program on campus at the University of Michigan.
Sources Consulted for History of Bureau of School Services
History compiled from the following sources: Letter to Schools from the University of Michigan (vol. I, no. 1, June 1948; and vol. IV, no. 2, November 1951); University of Michigan Office of the Registrar history (finding aid), Accreditation Standards, 1991-92 (Bureau of Accreditation and School Improvement Studies, School of Education, University of Michigan); The University of Michigan List of Exemplary School Programs, 1990-91 (University of Michigan, Ann Arbor); The University of Michigan Accredited Schools, 1990-1991 (University of Michigan, Ann Arbor); and The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey, vol. 5 (University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, 1977).
The records of the Bureau of School Service are comprised of 166 linear feet spanning the dates 1871 to 1992. The record group has been divided into three series: Administrative Files, Accreditation Inspection Reports, and Detroit High School Study Commission.
Education--Michigan.; Schools--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Committee on Diploma Schools.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; Education, Secondary--Michigan.; High Schools--Michigan.; School management and organization--Michigan.; Accreditation (Education); Detroit High School Study Commission.; North Central Association of Colleges and Schools (U.S.); University of Michigan. Bureau of Cooperation with Educational Institutions.
Contributors:
Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Robinson, Remus, 1904-1970.; Whitney, Allen Sisson, 1857-1944.
- Administrative Files
  The Administrative Files (1875-1930s, 1952-1965) are composed of one linear foot of minutes and reports of various committees, correspondence, and general and miscellaneous material pertaining to the accreditation program. This, plus the two bound volumes of accreditation inspection reports (1892-1907), was the main body of the 1953 accession. Also within these files are three folders of correspondence, 1952-1965, of Kenneth Vance, who served as the School Library Consultant. The majority of the correspondence is directed to Vance and contains thanks for his suggestions and visits, as well as invitations to speak at various functions.
  - General and Miscellaneous 1914-1930s, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Kenneth Vance 1952-1965, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Minutes and Reports
    - Committee on Cooperation with Educational Institutions 1932-1933 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Diploma Schools 1884-1904, 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - Committee on Relations with Institutions of Higher Education 1932-1933 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Relations with Secondary Schools 1933 (Box 1)
    - Report on comparative success of diploma and examination students 1875-1879 (Box 1)
    - University Committee on Accredited Schools 1930-1932 (Box 1)
- Accreditation Inspection Reports 1871-1992
  The Accreditation Inspection Reports (1871-1992), of which there are 163 linear feet, make up the bulk of the collection. These records include inspection reports, done by the Bureau and its predecessors, as well as reports submitted to the university's accreditation program by the individual schools. The files vary in size and content, but include information such as the following: student demographics, teacher education, curriculum, support facilities, class schedules, correspondence, population of city, enrollment, number of teachers, number of recitations, graduates attending higher education, employment practices, library facilities, laboratory facilities, school income, counseling standards, health programs, policies and objectives, guidance programs, administrator qualifications, and financial data. Some accreditation files of the North Central Association are also included.
  The earliest accreditation inspection reports are located in two bound volumes at the beginning of the collection. These were part of the 1953 accession and span the dates 1892 to 1907, although reports of the North Central Association for 1905 are included with the unbound reports. Reports are in rough alphabetical order by city and primarily include information about the instructors, number of students, size of library, and other brief comments about the school. They are not filed alphabetically with the rest of the reports as they were not easily separable. The bound volumes also include early reports for schools outside of Michigan. Additionally, there is one folder of unbound accreditation reports done in 1905 for non-Michigan schools. See the folder listing for the names of the schools included in the 1905 reports. The remainder of the accreditation inspection reports are filed alphabetically by city and then alphabetically by school name. An attempt was made to list varying names that the school used during its history and to cross reference schools to other cities and/or schools as appropriate. There were a number of loose reports that were part of the 1953 accession that have been interfiled with the 1996 accession as a matter of convenience to the researcher. These were largely reports of the North Central Association.
  Notes found within the collection indicate that university reports were not requested during the 1939/40 school year and that reports on school visits for the years 1879 to 1904 are available in the University of Michigan Registrar record group (box 11).
  References to these school visits and reports can be found scattered throughout a variety of other University of Michigan record groups. There are also letters within the papers of university president James B. Angell pertaining to school visits. One should consult the volumes of calendars of Angell's letters for examples.
  - Miscellaneous Records 1892-1907
    - 1892-1907, 2 Bound Volumes (Box 1)
    - Non-Michigan schools 1905 (Box 1)
      Franklin School (Cincinnati, Ohio); Howe School (Lima, Indiana); Hurley High School (Hurley, Wisconsin); South Bend High School (South Bend, Indiana)
  - A-C
    - Ada
      - St. Patrick High School 1924-1945 (Box 2)
    - Addison
      - Addison Community High School 1916-1992 (Box 2)
    - Adrian
      - Adrian High School 1871-1992 (Box 2)
      - Adrian Catholic Central High School 1947-1961 (Box 2)
      - Adrian Lenawee Christian School 1987-1992 (Box 2)
      - Madison High School 1959-1992 (Box 2)
      - Madison High School #2, 1958- 1985/86 (Box 2)
      - Raisin Valley Seminary 1905 (Box 3)
      - St. Joseph Academy 1924-1975 (Box 3)
      - St. Joseph High School 1927-1940 (Box 3)
      - St. Mary's High School 1940-1946 (Box 3)
    - Akron
      - Akron High School 1926-1958 (Box 3)
    - Alanson
      - Littlefield High School 1928-1979 (Box 3)
    - Alabaster
      - Alabaster High School 1933-1936 (Box 3)
    - Alba
      - Alba Rural Architectural School 1924-1973 (Box 3)
    - Albion
      - Albion Senior High School 1890-1992 (Box 3)
      - Washington Gardner High School (see Albion High School) (Box 3)
    - Algonac
      - Algonac High School 1918-1992 (Box 3)
    - Allegan (Box 4)
      - Allegan High School 1890-1992 (Box 4)
    - Allendale
      - Allendale High School 1979-1992 (Box 4)
    - Allen Park
      - Allen Park High School 1920-1992 (Box 4)
      - Cabrini High School 1964-1991 (Box 4)
    - Alma
      - Alma High School 1900-1992 (Box 4)
    - Almont
      - Almont Junior/Senior High School 1921-1991 (Box 4)
    - Alanson
      - Littlefield Public School 1960 (Box 4)
    - Alpena
      - Alpena High School 1884-1991 (Box 5)
      - St. Anne High School 1929-1949 (Box 5)
      - St. Bernard High School 1931-1950 (Box 5)
    - Alpha
      - Alpha High School 1921-1966 (Box 5)
    - Amasa
      - Amasa High School 1918-1956 (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor
      - Community High School circa 1930, 1975-1992 (Box 5)
      - Gabriel Richard High School 1908-1992 (Box 5)
      - Grace Bible Christian Academy 1975 (Box 5)
      - Greenhills High School 1974-1990 (Box 5)
      - Holy Ghost Fathers Mission Seminary 1952-1953 (Box 5)
      - Huron High School 1970-1992 (Box 6)
      - Pioneer High School 1871-1992 (Box 6)
      - St. Thomas the Apostle High School 1905-1977 (Box 6)
      - University Hospital School 1927-1941 (Box 6)
    - Arcadia
      - Arcadia (Township) High School 1920-1957 (Box 6)
    - Armada
      - Armada Area High School 1913-1992 (Box 6)
    - Ashley
      - Ashley High School 1925-1963 (Box 7)
    - Athens
      - Athens High School 1912-1992 (Box 7)
    - Atlanta
      - Atlanta Community School 1924-1991 (Box 7)
    - Auburn
      - Bay City Western High School 1906-1992 (Box 7)
    - Auburn Heights
      - Avondale High School 1937-1992 (Box 7)
    - Au Gres
      - Au Gres-Sims High School 1937-1991 (Box 7)
    - Augusta
      - Augusta High School 1914-1949 (Box 7)
      - W.K. Kellogg Consolidated School 1929-1941 (Box 7)
    - Bad Axe
      - Bad Axe High School 1906-1992 (Box 8)
    - Baldwin
      - Baldwin High School 1931-1991 (Box 8)
    - Bancroft
      - Bancroft High School 1926-1937 (Box 8)
    - Bangor
      - Bangor High School 1903-1992 (Box 8)
    - Baraga
      - Baraga High School 1915-1992 (Box 8)
    - Baroda
      - Baroda High School 1929-1956 (Box 8)
    - Barryton
      - Barryton Rural Agricultural School 1918-1966 (Box 8)
    - Bath
      - Bath High School 1924-1992 (Box 9)
    - Battle Creek
      - Battle Creek Academy 1935-1992 (Box 9)
      - Battle Creek Central High School circa 1872, 1905-1991 (Box 9)
      - Harper Creek High School 1929-1991 (Box 9)
      - Lakeview High School 1924-1992 (Box 10)
      - Pennfield High School 1957-1992 (Box 10)
      - Percy Jones Institute 1946 (Box 10)
      - St. Philip (Catholic Central) High School 1965-1992 (Box 10)
    - Bay City
      - All Saints Central High School 1968-1992 (Box 10)
      - Bangor Township Schools 1955 (Box 10)
      - Bay City Central High School 1929-1992 (Box 10)
      - John Glenn High School 1966-1992 (Box 11)
      - Holy Rosary Academy 1916-1925 (Box 11)
      - St. James High School 1905-1967 (Box 11)
      - St. Joseph High School 1939-1967 (Box 11)
      - St. Mary High School 1914-1966 (Box 11)
      - St. Stanislaus High School 1929-1967 (Box 11)
      - Visitation High School 1950-1960 (Box 11)
      - T.L. Handy High School 1947-1990 (Box 11)
      - West Catholic Central High School (see St. Mary High School) (Box 11)
    - Bay Port
      - Bay Port High School (became Elton Pigeon Bay Port High School) 1930-1955 (Box 11)
    - Bear Lake
      - Bear Lake High School 1915-1991 (Box 11)
    - Beaverton
      - Beaverton High School 1913-1991 (Box 12)
    - Belding
      - Belding Area School 1902-1992 (Box 12)
    - Bellaire
      - Bellaire High School 1908-1992 (Box 12)
    - Belleville
      - Belleville High School 1929-1992 (Box 12)
    - Bellevue (Box 13)
      - Bellevue High School 1907-1992 (Box 13)
    - Benton Harbor
      - Benton Harbor Senior High School 1905-1992 (Box 13)
      - St. John High School 1929-1969 (Box 13)
    - Benzonia
      - Benzie Central High School 1916-1992 (Box 13)
      - Benzonia Academy 1912-1929 (Box 13)
    - Bergland
      - Bergland Township Rural Agricultural School 1919-1966 (Box 13)
    - Berkley
      - Berkley High School 1927-1992 (Box 14)
    - Berrien Springs
      - Andrews (University) Academy 1963-1992 (Box 14)
      - Berrien Springs High School 1914-1992 (Box 14)
      - Emmanuel Missionary Academy 1916-1962 (Box 14)
    - Bessemer
      - A.D. Johnston High School/Bessemer High School 1903-1989 (Box 14)
    - Beverly Hills
      - Beverly Hills Groves High School 1962-1992 (Box 14)
    - Big Rapids
      - Big Rapids (Central) High School 1902-1992 (Box 15)
      - Ferris State College High School (also known as Ferris Institute High School) 1905-1976 (Box 15)
    - Birch Run
      - Birch Run High School 1929-1992 (Box 15)
    - Birmingham
      - Big Beaver High School 1937-1952 (Box 15)
      - Birmingham High School (see Seaholm High School) (Box 15)
      - Birmingham Groves High School (see Beverly Hills Groves High School) (Box 15)
      - Brother Rice High School 1963-1992 (Box 15)
      - Detroit Country Day High School 1927-1990 (Box 15)
      - (Wylie) Groves High School 1962-1985 (Box 16)
        (see also Beverly Hills High School)
      - Marian High School 1963-1985 (Box 16)
        (see also Bloomfield Hills)
      - (Earnest W.) Seaholm High School (formerly Birmingham High School) 1902-1992 (Box 16)
      - Troy Township Rural Agricultural School (see Big Beaver) (Box 16)
    - Blanchard
      - Montabella High School 1978-1992 (Box 16)
      - Blanchard High School/Rolland Township Rural Agricultural School 1928-1965 (Box 16)
    - Blissfield
      - Blissfield High School 1907-1992 (Box 16)
    - Bloomfield Hills
      - Academy of Sacred Heart 1955-1991 (Box 16)
      - Andover High School 1935-1992 (Box 17)
      - Cranbrook 1930-1988 (Box 17)
      - Kingswood School / Cranbrook 1932-1985 (Box 17)
      - Lahser High School 1969-1992 (Box 17)
      - Marian High School (Box 18)
        (see also Birmingham, 1963-1992)
      - Roeper City and Country School 1982-1988 (Box 18)
    - Bloomingdale
      - Bloomingdale High School 1915-1992 (Box 18)
    - Boyne City
      - Boyne City High School 1906-1992 (Box 18)
    - Boyne Falls
      - Boyne Falls High School 1927-1992 (Box 18)
    - Breckenridge
      - Breckenridge Junior/Senior High School 1918-1991 (Box 18)
    - Breedsville
      - Breedsville High School 1931 (Box 19)
    - Brethren
      - Brethren High School 1927-1989 (Box 19)
    - Bridgeport
      - Bridgeport Community High School circa 1964, 1986-1992 (Box 19)
    - Bridgman
      - Bridgman High School 1923-1992 (Box 19)
    - Brighton
      - Brighton High School 1918-1992 (Box 19)
    - Brimley
      - Brimley High School 1922-1992 (also called Superior Bay Mills Township Rural Agricultural School and Superior Township Rural Agricultural High School) (Box 20)
    - Britton
      - Britton-Macon Area High School 1916-1991 (Box 20)
    - Bronson
      - Bronson High School 1908-1992 (Box 20)
    - Brookfield Township (see Owendale) (Box 20)
    - Brooklyn
      - Columbia Central High School 1915-1992 (also Brooklyn High School) (Box 20)
    - Brown City
      - Brown City High School 1925-1992 (Box 21)
    - Buchanan
      - Buchanan High School 1902-1992 (Box 21)
    - Buckley
      - Buckley High School 1922-1964 (also known as Hanover Township Unit Agricultural School and Buckley Consolidated Agricultural School) (Box 21)
    - Burnips
      - Burnips High School 1940 (Box 21)
    - Burr Oak
      - Burr Oak High School 1907-1991 (Box 21)
    - Burton
      - Atherton High School 1974-1992 (Box 21)
      - Bendle High School circa 1931, 1974-1992 (Box 21)
      - Bentley High School circa 1958, 1974-1992 (Box 21)
    - Byron
      - Byron Area High School 1922-1992 (Box 22)
    - Byron Center
      - Byron Center High School 1928-1992 (Box 22)
  - C-D
    - Cadillac
      - Cadillac High School 1929-1991 (Box 22)
    - Caledonia
      - Caledonia High School 1922-1990 (Box 22)
    - Calumet
      - Calumet High School, (1895 ?) 1905-1992 (Box 23)
    - Camden
      - Camden-Frontier High School 1916-1992 (Box 23)
    - Canton
      - Plymouth Centennial Educational Park, (1900 ?) 1980-1982 (includes Plymouth Canton High School, Plymouth Salem High School, and Plymouth Christian Academy) (Box 23)
    - Capac
      - Capac (Community) Junior/Senior High School 1915-1991 (Box 23)
    - Carleton
      - Airport Senior High School 1926-1992 (Box 24)
    - Carney
      - Carney High School 1960-1976 (Box 24)
    - Caro
      - Caro Community High School 1906-1992 (Box 24)
    - Carrollton
      - Carrollton High School 1986-1992 (Box 24)
    - Carson City
      - Crystal High School 1914-1992 (Box 24)
    - Carsonville
      - Carsonville-Port Sanilac High School 1925-1992 (Box 24)
    - Caseville
      - Casevill High School 1960-1992 (Box 24)
    - Cass City
      - Cass City High School 1906-1992 (Box 25)
    - Cassopolis
      - Cassopolis (Ross Beatty) High School 1902-1992 (Box 25)
    - Cedar Lake
      - Cedar Lake Academy (Great Lakes Academy) 1932-1992 (Box 25)
    - Cedar Springs
      - Cedar Springs High School 1906-1992 (Box 25)
    - Cedarville (Clark Township)
      - Cedarville High School 1932-1992 (Box 25)
    - Cement City
      - Cement City High School (later Columbia Central High School in Brooklyn) 1929-1963 (Box 25)
    - Center Line
      - Center Line High School 1926-1992 (Box 26)
      - St. Clement High School 1927-1992 (Box 26)
    - Central Lake
      - Central Lake High School 1908-1992 (Box 26)
    - Centreville